Hi and welcome to this launch event
session on what's new in developer
tools.
You probably know us by now but my name
is Peter Borring and with me today I
have Stephen Balslev and Espen
uh Kristoffersen.
And as always we have a pretty packed
agenda. We'll have Stephen start out
talking about some of the investments
we've done with the VS Code extension
itself.
And and and related scenarios.
Espen will come and talk about the
introduction of namespaces which is a
which is a huge thing.
And he'll continue talking about tools
for documenting
apps.
Then I'll talk about investments we've
done to investigate and troubleshoot.
And then we'll hear about
improvements for the AL language and for
code authoring. I'll do a small intro to
GitHub Copilot chat. And end off with an
update on AppSource and AppSource
transact really.
But
maybe we should start with Stephen.
Please tell us more about the new
scenarios in our Visual Studio Code
extension. Yes, let's talk about that
one first.
When you install the AL language
extension you now have the option to
install or switch to a pre-release
version. With the pre-release you get
early access to bug fixes, previews, and
future functionality.
You can also use the pre-release as an
alternative to unpacking and manually
installing the AL language extension
from Business Central inside our preview
builds.
Within the Visual Studio Code extension
page it's super easy to switch between
versions. You can go from a release
version
to a pre-release version, try something
out, and come back to the release
version quite easily.
One thing we introduced with the preview
functionality is the ability to install
the AL language extension on Linux.
With our mission to empower every AL
developer out there, we now have the
option to use the AL language extension
from your favorite Linux subsystem.
Including using it on Windows subsystem
for Linux.
So, I I encourage all the Linux fans out
there to try it out and give us feedback
on GitHub. But, let's have a look at it.
So, before
doing this,
I pre-configured my WSL.
And I installed Visual Studio Code, I
installed the the .NET framework, and I
installed Edge browser. So, now I'm
ready to start coding. I can just do WSL
to start it up. I can start VS Code.
And now you'll notice that I have
Visual Studio Code for Linux. So, down
here somewhere we have a Visual Studio
Code icon, and it has a nice little
penguin on it, which is really cool.
So, I can run Visual Studio Code from
Linux on my Windows machine here using
the Windows subsystem for Linux. And of
course, I have installed my AL language
extension, and in this I have installed
the pre-release version, so I can get
started. This is all I need to to have
in order to get started with cloud
development, and I'll do just that. So,
let's see.
AL Go.
Let's do a new project. Let's make it
for the this release here.
We have a Hello World. I want to use a
cloud sandbox.
And then I need to download some
samples. Okay, that didn't work. So, I
need to change the
the sandbox here to my
preview sandbox, we're still in preview.
There we go.
And I'll download the symbols.
Once the symbols are downloaded,
I can set my breakpoint and I can start
debugging.
And because I've installed Edge for
Linux,
the Edge browser will pop up
and I can start debugging.
And we'll see it starts here on the page
as I would expect normal debugging
capabilities now from Linux.
So, go check it out.
Try the AL extension for Linux and let
us know what you think.
Another thing we added as a preview is
syntax highlighting for DevOps. You can
now install an extension that will allow
you to get color coding on AL code when
you have it in DevOps.
Also, go try this out and let us know
what you think about it.
With that, over to you Espen to talk
about namespaces.
Thank you, Stephen.
My name is Espen and I'm going to talk
to you about one of the major new
features in the AL language, namespaces.
A namespace is a way of organizing
different names or identifiers that
belongs to a certain group or context.
It's a common way to organize
information not only in programming
languages, but also in the real world.
Think about books in a library.
The author can be considered a
namespace. It's a way to disambiguate
books with the same name
and is normally used when the books are
organized on the shelves.
Imagine Raymond Chandler's great novel
The Big Sleep
from 1939.
In a library or a bookstore, it would be
in the crime section under Chandler,
Raymond.
Another author that writes a book with
the same name
about how to improve your nightly sleep.
It may be found on the health section
and that author's name.
As humans, we tend to structure
information in a hierarchical system.
Think about the file system on on your
computer. An example from our world
would be the customer table. The
customer is an entity that you sell to.
It makes sense to put that in a name
space called sales together with all
other AL objects related to selling.
Grouping of objects makes it easier to
discover objects and items belonging to
a specific group. In the bookstore
examples, if you're looking for a book
that is a crime novel,
you know what section to start in. The
hard part is, of course, to create a
good taxonomies taxonomy of your
objects.
There's probably not one single right
way to do it, but even the good ones can
provide you with a lot of help. Name
spaces can also help reducing name
clashes.
Again, looking for book named The Big
Sleep by an author named Chandler
Raymond,
um in the crime section will most likely
only yield a single hit.
This is the same in our domain.
So, let's look at a small demo here.
This is a small example without name
spaces. And the way we have built the
name space feature is that you opt in by
actually declaring a name space. This
piece piece of code, even when I hover
over the individual objects here,
they are showing that the
base application I'm using here is
actually name spaced. This is the
environment information code unit and
it's in the system.environment name
space.
But everything compiles. I can deploy
this to a service which already is name
spaced. But let me add my own namespace
to this and let's see what is happening.
You declare a namespace as the first
line in a in a source file or the first
non-comment line.
And if I choose to put this in
Microsoft.Demo,
let me just correct the casing here.
You can see what happens here
immediately. All the places where I
reference another object,
I get an error because they cannot be
found.
The only objects which can be found here
now in this code unit
is objects from the same namespace. And
actually, I have already created another
code unit which I put in the
Microsoft.Demo namespace.
So, what do I do now?
Luckily, we have added
a number of code actions. And the one
I'm using for here is either add a using
statement. That's a a way to say, "I
want all the objects from the in this
case Microsoft.Sales.Customer
namespace
available in this code unit." So, I can
choose that. And it adds a namespace for
me.
And suddenly,
you can see here the customer is now no
longer an error, but is actually found.
What is also interesting here that you
actually are able to get some more
information here about
for instance, that the application
method is an enum defined in the
Receivable Payables
namespace, which is a sub namespace of
Microsoft.Finance.
So, it already here you get some more
information about
what this actually is.
And let me continue here.
And as you noted, I had another option.
That was to fully qualify the name.
And in this case, it's the system
environment
that is the namespace for environment
information. Let's Let me do fully
qualify. And as you can see immediately,
the code action helps me here and is
adding
the environment information. This goes
for all the other cases here where I
have used objects. This one I choose to
qualify fully
or at the using statement.
And you can see this is also the case
when you do the the syntax where you
actually navigate to an object name.
I have only
the enums which are either in
in the Microsoft demo namespace or in
the Microsoft sales.customer available
here.
But I can choose to either
fully qualify or add a using statement.
So, I will fully qualify fully qualify
this as well.
Like this. And suddenly I have actually
fixed this code unit to work with
namespaces.
And I can deploy this
if I want to.
So, namespace is the syntax, as I
already said. This has to be the first
real statement in a source file.
It covers all the objects in the file.
You can only have one namespace per
file.
And you can nest namespaces in the
declaration, which means that in this
case, it's it's the namespace
system.environment
where environment is a sub namespace of
system.
The identifiers used in namespaces must
be CLS compliant, which means that they
have to start with a underscore
or a
a letter. You can have the same
namespace in many files, and you can
have the same namespace in multiple
modules. It's not tied to specific
module.
The using directives, they are
immediately after the namespace
declaration.
And the using directives brings all the
objects declared in that namespace into
scope, which means I can use them in
this source file.
There's no ordering.
But
when we look for an object, we will look
first in your own namespace, which means
that in this case, if I declared a
environment information code unit in my
own directions demo namespace, it will
be picked before any of those brought in
from the using statements.
In situations where I want to pick a
specific object and make sure that it's
not being confused with an object in
another namespace brought in with a
using statement, I can use
choose to use fully qualified names as
you saw before.
In some cases, this is a better way of
specifying names because that means that
there will be no way that this
object can be
ambiguous with another object in a
different namespace.
And if you have
a large source file where you use a
number of objects only a single time,
this may be the better solution.
When we introduce namespaces, we have
two rules, and those rules are also to
preserve compat- compatibility
with with old code.
So, you can only have one object of a
kind with the same name in the module.
Which means that kind name and and
module is unique.
And you can only have one object of a
kind with the same name in a namespace,
which also means that kind and fully
qual- fully qualified name is also
unique.
And here's some
bad news for now. We still have a fixes.
Um
we would like to lift some of the
restrictions and for instance, one of
those we are looking at is new name
spaced object can have names without a
fixes.
Which will take a little bit longer is
member of on objects.
Um but it's this
introduction of name spaces is for us a
way of moving at in a directions without
a fixes.
But it may take a while.
Name spaces, how should you proceed with
this?
You should wait
with name spacing your own code until
all your dependencies are name spaced.
The reason for that is that if you have
a dependency
on a module which is not
yet name spaced
and you start name spacing your own
code, it will break when your dependency
is being name spaced because suddenly it
will not be able to find
the
the object you previously referred to.
So wait until all your dependencies are
name spaced. That's important.
Choose a unique name for your name
spaces.
And the good practice is to choose
something that start with your company
name,
product, area, feature. But
you should make sure that the root is
definitely your own.
It should be stable
and non version specific
because renaming a name space is a
breaking change.
If you move an object from one name
space to another, those who referred to
the object where it were before
will be broken.
Yes, and it should be your own your
root.
Don't use system, don't use Microsoft,
don't use utility common or other
other names which can be
confused or used by others.
Choose your own and company name is a
good name.
So,
namespaces, the value of namespaces is
one of the values are discoverability
and navigability.
And luckily we have a good place to
surface this. So, if you actually want
to discover what is in different
namespaces, you can use the AL Explorer.
Now we have the group by namespace um
feature that allows you to simply see a
tree view of the namespaces that you
have in your in in the
your app and dependent app.
So, it's easy to figure out what is in
the Microsoft sales but custom namespace
for instance. You can look at all the
objects there
and and see what is related. And often
you will have a need to find a related
object to a certain area.
Go use AL Explorer for that.
We have also added here, as you can see,
namespaces a column so you can also get
some information about where this
actually belongs. What is this object
related to? It's a good and valuable
information.
And this actually
is a good segue to the next topic, AL
Doc, because that's also about
discoverability and a way of
investigating what is in a
in in in your source file and other
source files including our base app.
So, let's talk about our new
documentation tool,
AL Doc.
AL Doc produces reference documentation
from source.
So, what is reference documentation?
It's a special kind of documentation.
Reference documentation provides details
about programming elements associated
with technologies and languages,
including class libraries, object model,
programming language language
constructs.
And this is because consistency
is essential in reference documentation.
You want the same layout, standard
design, predictable heading structure,
so you know what you're looking at, for
instance, a In our case, our world now,
a table.
You would get the fields, you get the
keys, you get the methods,
information in the same way for all
tables being documented.
And you also want to have links with
related information. This is also a
common feature.
And
this is something that screams
automation because
I mean, we already have something which
is structured. The information is big. I
mean, in our case, the base app is very
big,
but it's also structured. So, if we can
use this structure to generate
documentation,
it's a good thing.
And reference documentation,
it improves discoverability.
Good
documentation can help you, us, ramp up
new developers.
It can help other partners using
your source code or our source code.
And it can serve as an anchor point for
more information as
as being an entry point for navigating
onto more specific, more detailed
information that could be some
very elaborate examples or something
like that.
Already today, for the AL language, we
are generating reference documentation.
We're doing that for our base
methods. You have probably already seen
that, and our
enums defined as a part of the core
compiler.
But now we actually want to take this
one step further and extend our
reference documentation to also cover
our application, but also give you the
opportunity to use it for your own
application.
So, what are we talking about here?
It's source as documentation.
For a couple of a couple of years ago,
we added XML documentation comment to
the AL language.
And the
biggest uh
uptake of this
for our own is in the system
application, where this piece of uh
documentation is from. As you can see
here, it already contains some valuable
information,
which is
interesting to use in documentation.
And as you can see here, today we we
only surface this information in
IntelliSense in in um in the code editor
here. Two examples. I mean,
either when hovering or also when using
the signature help.
What we want to do is something like
this, where we use it to generate online
documentation.
So, you can see here, there's already a
summary. Let's put that in a summary
under the share method.
There parameter information there. Put
there.
The structure of the method definition
in this case. Show the syntax, but also
use the
um information to create the name the
variable near or the parameter list.
We'll we'll help there.
And there's even a sample code here. A
piece small piece of sample
um added to this,
and that's also surfaced.
This tool has two purposes. It's one
tool called AL Doc, but it allows us to
create reference documentation for all
our first-party apps.
We're starting slowly, but we plan to do
it for all our apps.
And then we would like to allow you as
our partners to do the same for your
code base to help your
own partners or maybe internal
developers as a ramp up.
Help them understand the code. It's a
good practice and it also makes you
think about whenever you write a
comment,
how can you help someone else?
Let's talk a little bit about how it
works and then I will demo it.
This is all about transforming
information stored in an app file
into HTML as a static website.
And we have added this new tool AL Doc.
It resides in the V6 next to the ALC and
it has two primary commands.
One which is called AL Doc init. The
init command
initializes a
a folder
with the needed templates to show
AL
documentation reference documentation.
That's a one-time only and you will only
need to call that if you want to
initialize the
your documentation repo once again.
The other one AL Doc build, that is the
command you will run whenever you have
made changes or you want to update your
documentation from a .app file.
And the output of that is YAML files. It
create YAML files for the individual
objects, for the module, and for other
things, which is
containing the structure
together with the documentation you
wrote in your comments. It's just a text
format.
Then this is fed into the DocFX tool.
DocFX is a open source project initiated
by Microsoft, but it's open source.
And that is a project that combines
templates, YAML, and markdown into HTML.
And it also has a build method. And when
the build method is running with a
configuration,
it processes the YAML, markdown, and
templates, and creates a static website.
Let's look at how that works.
I have here
a small
piece of code.
Actually, let me start with how showing
you how it looks today.
This is a GitHub repo, and I have
initiated it with initialized it with
the
Bing Maps
sample that Freddy Christensen have
created.
I have enriched it a little bit with
some comments and name spaced it because
we are after all we are modern now.
But otherwise, this is just following
following the
aka.ms/algopte
and upload
the sample.
What I did after that was that I
actually
enabled GitHub pages.
GitHub pages is a way for you to have
some documentation next to your GitHub
project.
I chose here to use the docs folder as a
subfolder where I want to put my
documentation. And I created that one in
my repo.
And then I created another folder called
dog effects, which I initialized with AL
Doc.
And then I run the tool
as I described before. And what it gives
me is actually this nice documentation
ready-made.
I have an overview here with some
information from the
um this is actually mostly from the
manifest.
And then I have references here.
And you can see this is namespaces. I
named this namespace that with Freddy K
and Bing Maps.
There's a setup sub namespace here
where I can go to settings.
Not a lot of comments in there.
See in the setup, there's a little more.
And you can see there's a bunch of
methods here already. The structure's
there. Nice. There's a lot of comments.
But let's see. Let's try to add a
comment.
So, let's try to add some documentation
to the Bing Maps GeoCode code unit.
So, I'll write a documentation comment.
And already here, this is Copilot coming
with a suggestion.
We can stick with that saying this is
not
It's fine. We'll go with that. So, I
save this.
I build it.
It's quick.
Local build.
And then I go to the terminal window
here.
And as I mentioned before,
there is a
build command for AL Doc. I have already
run the AL init, so I'm just going to do
the
the build.
And it's fairly fast even on large
projects because
Yeah. Quick. Done. There's a warning.
Not a problem here.
And then I run the build here for
DocFX, which is the one that takes the
YAML, which was produced before, and now
creates HTML.
Let's see.
Takes a little bit longer.
It's also done. And then notice up here,
this is a Git repo, right?
So, there's some changes. First of all,
there's this change here. Oops.
Which is obviously the one I created.
Then I have this file.
This is actually the HTML file
um for the for the code unit. And as you
can see here,
suddenly
my comment is in here.
And the cross-reference also contains
this information.
Shouldn't worry a lot about that. Then
what I'll do now, add this.
Commit.
Thanks.
Then I can commit and push this, which
means that when I commit this
into my repo,
what happens is actually
if I go back here,
and
see now there's a small orange thing
here.
And uh there's something here about
deployments.
So, already now it's actually processing
my changes.
And
see the changes like that.
go back here.
Should be
almost done.
And let's see if we go to
code units
to your code
this
and
I have here the comment I just wrote.
In this case, I did all this manually,
but we will add this to a
So it's a part of AL Go for GitHub and
you can choose an opt-in for
automatically having
documentation like this generated.
That was all I had.
And Peter? Thank you, Asbjørn. It's
great to see that we finally have
namespace support in AL. And AL Doc will
really help with getting up-to-date
documentation on apps.
And both of these helps with
discoverability. And speaking of that,
let's talk about additional investments
in making it easier to discover,
investigate, and troubleshoot Business
Central.
So, imagine that
you want to investigate how a certain
functionality works.
Uh or you need to troubleshoot an issue
in production or in a sandbox
environment.
So, that involves um
provisioning a Visual Studio Code
workspace uh and project to investigate
and troubleshoot a customer environment.
Uh and it also involves knowledge and a
lot of manual steps. You need to open VS
Code, uh you need to create the project,
figure out the details about the
environment, the connection uh string,
the name, etc. Uh you might need to find
a session ID if you want to debug,
create a launch configuration with this
information, figure out what apps are
involved uh in the scenario to create
dependencies to those in an app.json.
You need to authenticate and you need to
download symbols.
So that that could take work and be hard
to figure out and it takes time.
And so imagine if you could automate
this to increase developer productivity
to empower tech-savvy consultants to
investigate apps and do light
troubleshooting with limited Visual
Studio Code knowledge.
And to empower support
to also troubleshoot faster and to lower
time to mitigate.
So let's see how we can do that
with some great new functionality. Let
me switch to the web client.
So let's have a look at a customer in
Business Central.
And I would like to investigate
this page a little bit more.
So I'm going to use my normal
investigation tool which is the page
inspector.
And I can open that with control alt F1
or from the help and support page.
And as you probably know you can open
the the table and view the data and you
can see the fields etc.
But we have a new option now called
explore page in Visual Studio Code.
And so let's try that out. So I'm I'm
going to click that.
And so what happens now is that Visual
Studio Code will open up.
It will create a dummy project.
It will create an app.json in that dummy
project with references to the
extensions that are required for the
page. So in the page inspector you might
know there's an extension tab. It will
be those extensions listed in that tab.
Then it will create a launch.json
configuration that we see here both for
a normal debugging session, a normal
attach and we see also the
session in there. It will actually
authenticate.
First time you authenticate you need to
do
you know a
special signing process with two factor
with code basically not two factor but
with a code in the client but I skipped
that.
It will download the symbols and then it
will ask if I want to debug Snapchat
debug regular debugging or or not debug.
And just for now let's not debug right
let's see what happened in VS code. So
it knew that I was on the customer page
so it opened up the source for the
customer card.
Um and apart from seeing all of the name
space and using statements that we heard
uh
um Espen talked about you can actually
also see all of the code for the page.
You can see the field you can see any
field validation you can see the
properties etc. etc.
Uh so this is a you know really fast way
to get in and investigate the source
behind of the code for a page.
So uh let's let's you know dig a little
further maybe we want to understand what
happens on the the table behind the page
so we have the source table being the
customer
and I can actually you know I can
control click with a hyperlink to go to
customer or do F12 and jump to the
customer table and I can see any kind of
field validation or other logic on the
table here as well. We also added a new
feature in the previous release which
was the AL Explorer.
So let's open that.
And we can go and find our customer
card.
And we can see that the customer card is
in the actually that doesn't see that
let me just
minimize.
Uh it doesn't show that well here but
it's in the Microsoft sales dot customer
name space.
And so we could group by name space for
example and we could drill into that and
you know oh I have to just remove this
so we can see everything.
Uh we can drill into the uh sales and
the customer name space and see what
else in that. So this is a great way to
discover. Again, I only had one click
from the client. I came in here. As long
as it's the extensions which were used
on the page, I can see the content. I
could see for example that we have a
customer list. That looks interesting. I
could I could run it
and see it in the client, you know,
quickly jump to the client to see the
list. So that's maybe not that exciting,
but it's going to show the list. We can
see that later. Uh I can also jump to
the source, right? Directly from here,
jump to the now customer list source.
All of this just with a single click.
Now, we talked about debugging also. So
while the first scenario here might be,
you know, that's that could be a
consultant who wanted to go in and do
light investigation reading AL, figuring
out how a trigger logic or validation
worked, part of specification also in
that process to understand how things
works. It could also be a developer.
Uh the next scenario here about uh
troubleshooting, that could be all of
the roles. It could be a developer or a
consultant doing light troubleshooting
or support for that matter. But again,
we're in VS Code. We did exactly the
same as we saw before.
Uh we can switch to debug mode. It will
do that automatically if I had entered
the regular debugging or the snapshot
debug that we saw before.
Uh but as I said, as part of creating
Visual Studio Code, it created three
configurations. So I have one for just
attaching and it put in the session ID
of my client. Uh normally you would find
that in help and support in a
troubleshoot section and put that in
manually, but here it's it's set up for
you automatically. It also creates a
snapshot profile here. That's if you
want to do
uh troubleshooting directly in
production, you cannot use the
the normal debugger, but you need to do
snapshots. It could also be that you
want to do um profiling, right? So, then
you would use the snapshot here.
And then maybe you just want to look at
the symbol. So, that's a that's a
request for that. But in the debugger,
you can pick between the different
launch. Let's do a normal debugging. So,
I'm just going to use the chosen a chat
request and I can use this play button
to start debugging and that will now
attach to the client that I have. We see
the session down here.
So, let's switch back to the client.
And let's say
yes, so this is the list that you saw
before, but let's go back to the card.
Let's say that I had a problem when I
entered in phone number a string, you
know, this
not that exciting, but just to trigger
an exception and hit the debugger,
right? So, I'm just going to do FFF
and return
and that will actually hit the debugger,
right? So, here we are exactly at the
line where we have the validation.
Still, I didn't do anything in VS. You
remember back from before, I just in
page inspector pressed the ability to
explore the page in Visual Studio Code.
Uh and then I can step through the code
and debug here.
But wait,
there's more.
If we go back to the client, let me just
stop this debugging session.
If we go back to the client, let's just
revert this
issue.
So, you can actually also explore from a
field. So, we have a list of the table
fields.
So, let's just say that I was still
interested in my phone number field,
which is this one. You see it
highlighted over here.
In the drop down for the field, you now
have an explore field in VS Code.
If I click that, it will, you know,
again provision VS Code,
download everything, create launch
configuration, etc., but it will bring
me to the source code for the table
field in the table. So, I can inspect it
there, right? So, I have two options
here, page and table.
And the last option is that if you go to
the help and support page that you
probably know, under the troubleshooting
session section, you have a new option
to attach debugger to this session.
It's basically going to do the same
again, but it will it will only put in
the base and system application
or extensions as as dependencies in the
VS Code project and as symbols for you
to explore, right? Because it doesn't
have any context like in the page that
we had before. So just to see a quick
overview of what you could do here, you
could explore the page in Visual Studio
Code from the page in inspector under
the page section. Again, you could do
the same under the field to see the
table field and you could go to the help
and support section and open
or attach from there. So
we have some permissions that you need
to have to do this. So for the attaching
help and support, that will show always,
but the options in the page inspector
will only appear if you have the
troubleshooting tools permission.
And that's similar to some other
functionality in the page inspector.
And just to recap again what happened in
Visual Studio Code is that we provision
it. If you don't have the AL Visual
Studio Code extension installed, we will
suggest it and and stop. We'll create a
dummy project with all the content
necessary and ask you whether you want
to troubleshoot or just investigate.
So some best practices on this.
Initially, you need to be patient. You
know, downloading symbols can take time,
so just wait until everything finishes
up and it asks whether you want to debug
or not.
You need to have access to the source
code to view it. You know, if you don't
have if it's under IP protection, just
like today, it will just show you empty
source, right? It will try to protect
the uh the the extension IP.
Still.
Um
we generate projects, so they will
accumulate. So, you know, you should
occasionally delete these so they don't
uh aggregate up. Um also, when you work
on this, if you already have VS Code
open and you initiate this, you can
actually reuse the currently open VS
Code and you can choose whether you want
to reuse the symbols as well if they
haven't changed or or or download new
versions of them. Uh and you can even
We'll talk about that later, but you can
even now also have a shared uh symbols
path where you can reuse uh symbols, so
you don't have to spend time on
downloading them.
As I said, we support both production
and sandboxes. You can only debug in the
latter.
And again, as I said, um this is a quick
way also for using the AL profiler from
within Visual Studio Code instead of the
inline profiler if you want to have, you
know, fine-grained details with
instrumentation.
So, we have some future ideas. Uh
building on top of this, there's no
commits right now, but, you know, it
would be great if instead of opening up
locally on VS Code and sort of that
content switching that you can actually
open it up in the cloud in CodeSpaces.
And also, as we saw now, it works on
symbols and fetching the source from the
the NST, but it would also be great if
it can actually integrate uh with uh
GitHub and pull source from there.
Either for the specific version deployed
um on the on the server that you have
attached to or to pull the latest if you
just want to have it as a starting point
and then go and develop on that
extension.
It would also be great if you could get
symbols for all extensions in one go if
you just want to investigate or for a
specific set of extensions, maybe from
the extension uh management page, uh for
example.
But try this out. Uh it's available in
the preview. When you watch this, it's
available in uh you know, the launch.
And give us feedback and uh
etc. and ideas and on on Viva, the
former Yema. So a couple of additional
comments on this
in the error details, you you know, you
know I have this ability to copy the
details and that also shows the call
stack. You can see that in purple at the
bottom right. That's another way of
getting some context about where the
problem is.
Also inside of the debugging experience
in the debug console, we now support
intellisense. So if you want to evaluate
something, we saw before that I type FFF
in the phone number. If I wanted to
evaluate that, I could get intellisense
on phone number in the console and and
just, you know,
it's great for discoverability of what
is in available during debugging but
also just productivity to not type it,
right? And it works on fields and locals
and globals and on member symbols. But
we don't have any evaluation of methods
that is supported for this.
So um
I talked about the AL profiler. Let's
recap just a little bit. So some
releases ago we introduced a couple of
great tools to investigate performance.
There was
profiling tools. So we had an in-client
performance profiler
that was accessible to customers,
consultants and developers. And we also
had an AL profiler in VS
code that allowed more sort of detailed
information for developers.
In the in-client profiler always and as
an option in the Visual Studio Code AL
profiler, we're using something that is
called sampling to to record what is
happening. And in this example, you can
see that it looks like, you know, we
have a sampling just a little bit above
100 milliseconds in both places. And
just, you know, quickly to recap
sampling, basically what sampling means
is that when we look at
what is happening, we look at fixed
interval. That's what we call the
sampling rate or the sampling interval,
right? And so, if you imagine multiple
methods um running,
we can only see what is running when
we're looking at the sampling point.
And so, that gives like a high-level
view of what is running.
There is an alternative, which is only
available from profiling in VS Code, and
that's called instrumentation, and that
basically looks continuously.
But, in the in-client profiler, and as
an option in the
profiler, you can use sampling, right?
And in this release,
we are giving you the option. So, the
default for now has been 100 ms. We're
now giving you the option to go a little
lower than that, 50 ms, or higher, 150
ms. So, that can give you more
granularity to see smaller operations,
or to limit the amount of data and only
focus on the large um you know, that
that that where time is spent,
basically. In the in-client profiler,
there's a new settings button that will
allow you to choose this. And in Visual
Studio Code, when you're using the
profiling type sampling, you have an
option called profile sampling interval,
where you can set the value between
these three options.
So, let's bring Stefan
back and talk about the investments that
we have in AL language.
Let's start this off by talking about
the biggest thing, the most noticeable
thing in the language changed this
release, and that is of course the
namespaces that has been talked about.
You can declare namespaces to
encapsulate your objects, add using
statements to get easy access to objects
in that namespace, and use fully
qualified names where needed, for
example, to resolve name conflicts.
Moving on to something maybe less
noticeable in the the changes we've
done, and that is the fact that we now
allow you to implicitly convert variants
to dictionaries and lists. And as part
of that we added two new methods in the
variant type, is dictionary and is list.
Another big change is a new data type
called secure text. This is a new
variable and parameter data type type
you can use to protect the data it holds
from being debugged.
It does not protect it from being shared
outside of Business Central, but it
protects you protects it
as you are debugging using the Business
Central debugger. This applies to normal
debugging as well as snapshot debugging.
You construct the secure text data in a
non-debuggable method, and then you can
pass it on to relevant methods without
having to worry about it being exposed.
Let's see how that could look like.
Here I have a demo project that I'm
going to try and run. So, I'm going to
run the debugger.
And it will publish my application to a
sandbox.
And from here
I can invoke this action that will do
some work with secret text. So, let's
see how that works.
I'm going to click this process data
action.
And yes, my debugger breaks here.
So, now I can start debugging and let's
see where we can use secret text here.
I'll start by going into this method.
So, I'll do the step into.
And then I'll step over the setup here.
Here I have a new variable called a
header value and it is the type secret
text.
It's going to be set using a function
from this provider called get API key,
and I can see that the get API key
returns secret text here.
So, this is interesting.
As this value is created inside this get
API key function,
I would expect that it has been marked
with non-debuggable, and I can verify
that by looking at the source or I can
just
click the step into
and see that it actually steps over
because I can't debug into this
function.
So, now I have a value that is of type
secret text. And if I go and look at the
value using the hover, I'll see hidden
value.
If I go look at the locals here,
I will see hidden value. And even if I
go down here and check the header value,
it's still a hidden value. So, I can't
get to this value no matter what I do.
But I do I can't put it in a function
here, so I can call this function. Let's
see what that does.
So, this is a function that will create
a request message for me that I can use
to send data outside of Business
Central.
In a normal scenario, you would set a
request URI like this. And you you can
also get out the request URI. And as you
can see in the locals, we can now see
the value of this request URI. So, it's
not really hidden. But we now have the
option to hide the URL in case you have,
for example, an API key in your URL.
So, here I have a situation where I used
to set secret request URI.
And again again, I'm calling a function
that I expect is marked with
non-debuggable and is returning a secret
text. You can see it here. It's
returning a secret text.
So, if I press the left F11 here, it
will step over it and not step into it.
If I then go and try and get out this
request URI
like this,
I will see that the request URI can't be
fetched. It will still be empty here.
So, there's no way to get the secret out
of the URI.
We also have headers for these things.
And you can add a normal header. You can
also add a header using a secure a
secret text.
And again, you can get out the headers.
If it's a normal header, you can get it
out and you can see the header values.
Yeah, we got out the thing that we put
in.
We can clear that. We can try and get
out the value that is a secret text. And
no, we cannot do that. The reason why I
put this in an if statement is because
this will actually not find this value.
So, it'll throw an exception.
I can of course also use the secret text
in a body. So, I can put it in the
content of my message.
Now, I'm done creating this nice little
request message and I can pass that back
to my method here.
And now it's important to remember that
this method returned an object that
contains secret data. It's not a secret
text
uh
variable here, but it has secret data in
here. So, I shouldn't return this in a
public function. I should keep it within
the scope of my extension, within the
privacy of my extension. You can't get
to it from debugging.
But, if somebody else got this message
object and change the URL, they could
send it somewhere else and expose the
data. So, keep it for yourself, so to
speak.
Of course, you can continue using this
and you can send it on
uh to other methods within your
application and you can keep the data
safe from any prying eyes you doing
debugging.
So, that's the secret text.
Let's move on to field groups. For a
while now, you've been able to add
fields to an existing field group, but
many have noticed that it's impossible
to add fields to a field group that
doesn't exist in the base object.
In this example here,
it would be impossible for me to add a
brick field group to the GL entry table,
simply because there is no brick field
group to begin with in the base
application.
Now, we made it possible for you to add
fields to a field group that doesn't
exist, thereby enabling the scenario
where we want to add a field group for
bricks,
so you can show your GL entries in a
nice way.
The add last continues to append fields
either to an empty field group or to the
existing field group and it continues to
exclude duplicates. So, if two
extensions are adding the same field,
the field will only appear once. On
table fields, you now also have the
option to control if a field can be used
in profile customization.
Previously, you had to add a field to
the page in order for it to be used in
profile customization, but now you can
also choose from table fields if you
have the right permissions.
With the allow in customization
property, you can control if a certain
field should never be possible to add in
a profile customization.
On pages, you also have more control.
Here, you can now set the analysis mode
enabled to false on that specific list
page where detailed analysis
capabilities are not usable.
We have two new extended data types. The
barcode extended data type can be set on
fields where you want the scanner button
to appear when you're using a device,
making it much easier for people to
enter data using their device camera.
We also have the rich text extended data
type that enables you to add rich
content capabilities to your fields.
It requires multi-line to be set to true
and it must be within a group of its own
or you will not get the rich content
editor.
But, let's pause a little here.
Rich content fields are actually more
than just a way of formatting the
display of the field. It gives you the
capability that you would expect from a
rich text editor, like formatting,
adding images, links, and so forth,
making it ideal for very rich content
creation.
At this point, it does have some
restrictions,
like the fact that it needs to be alone
in its own group, so you cannot use it
in a repeater or in in an existing group
with other fields.
Likewise, you cannot currently customize
the toolbar. And you have limited
limited personalization capabilities. As
a developer, you also need to know that
it requires backing by types without
size, like text.
And the rich content value is HTML with
inline images.
In the coming releases, we'll continue
to work on the rich text editor and its
capabilities, so I'm sure we'll talk
about this soon again.
Now it's time for queries. We made it
possible to use queries in run object
for actions, and now you can set the
usage category to have a query show up
in the tell me when a user search for
it.
And with the about title and about text,
you can build rich teaching tips, all of
which can help your users get the most
out of the queries you've built.
Combining data for use in Excel reports
used to be difficult and often resulted
in complicated matrix-like data tables
in Excel.
Now with the Excel layout multiple data
sheets property, you can split up each
data item into its own data sheet.
With multiple data sheets, you
significantly reduce the complexity and
improve not only the size of the report,
but also the rendering performance and
the complexity of authoring.
Individual data sets also allows you to
get the most out of modeling and
building with power pivot in Excel.
Speaking of power,
Peter, what about AL coding powers?
Yeah, what about
code authoring? So, just like with the
AL language, we have a collection of
enhancements to make everyday code
authoring more productive.
So, let's uh
jump straight into it.
Uh Visual Studio Code supports an editor
concept called inlay hints, and these
are additional information inline in
source code to help you understand what
the code does.
And in this release, we're adding the
ability to get inlay hints for AL
parameter names and for return types.
And so here is an example that I marked
out where you see that we're calling a
method process document with true false
true. And you might wonder, what does
that method do?
Of course you can you know, navigate to
it you know, to figure it out, but you
can with the inlay hints enabled, you
can use control alt and you can then
switch and then the editor will insert
basically the the names of the
parameters, right? So here you see that
instead of true false true, we can see
that it's include um
start date and include end date and the
delete when done parameters that you set
in this way. And the names there of
course comes from the parameter
definition on on this method. And if you
see the line below, you can even see
that we also show the return value,
right? So for the line below, you see
that integer at the end is the return
value for this method. So this really
helps quickly toggle and this will
happen for all of the code in the view,
not just for one for the one method that
you are looking at, but for everything
in in the editor view.
And so
to enable this, you first need to enable
it as a feature in Visual Studio Code.
And so there's a setting the editor dot
inlay hint dot enabled where you can set
the the standard behavior. Do you want
it to be off or always on or do you want
to have a behavior where you use a
shortcut key to hide it or to show it,
right? So that's that's what you can
choose.
And then in Visual Studio Code, you can
also then um
influence how these inlay hints are
shown. You can decide the the font
family and size and and the padding
here.
But then you also have to enable it for
AL, right? So we have a property or two
properties in the AL inlay hints
collection for enabling whether you want
to see it on function return types or
for the parameter names, right? So, to
to have this functionality, enable it in
VS Code and for AL.
Okay, another feature that we build is
that if you're working with
with labels, right? You might be using
them for user messages. When you are
using that label variable,
maybe you want to see what is inside
that
that label, right? And so, instead of
having to navigate to that or use peak
definition, you can now just hover over
that. So, in this example, you see that
we hover over the user message in the
message call and you can see that the
label value is user message. So, that's
makes it a little bit easier to see
label
values.
Another IntelliSense investment is when
you have multiple overloads, we then
pick you know, we are smarter at picking
the recommended signature.
So, before you would have to scroll
through those different options. In this
scenario, you see that there's, you
know, six options and this is showing
the first of those six options when we
call process, but now we will try to
match the parameters that you specified
so far and then reorder the suggestions
here to the ones that is,
you know, the first basically our best
match to what you've written so far. And
then we order the remaining ones in the
order based on
on the provided parameters. So, that
just just make it easier for you to work
with
with um
with methods with with overloads, right?
Also, again, IntelliSense when you're
working with methods that accept keys,
like the set current keys, we now also
list the available keys in the
IntelliSense, right? So, in this
scenario, you see I started typing and I
get the key suggestions. We still also
allow, of course, specific fields to
select those if you want to, for
instance, short on those.
Now,
commonly when you want to understand the
relationship in source, you can use the
find all references functionality in
Visual Studio Code.
And we have improved that to now also
work on trigger and system methods and
trigger events. That's a portal on page
and table fields, on page actions, and
on table methods, triggers, and events.
And we will now, you know, find only the
the references that are truly relevant,
right? So, if you are looking, for
instance, at a trigger here, the the on
insert trigger, for example, on the
customer, you can see that the reference
count in the code lens at the top there,
the 17,
shows how much, you know, how many
places this is used. And you can then
use the find all references to go
through and view all of these uses,
right?
So, then again, that is something that
improves your productivity to see these
relations.
When we then talk about project
handling,
we heard
asks for,
for, you know, ever since the first day,
when you use the AL Go
command to create a new default project,
it uses the document folders in Windows,
right? And so, we have the suggestion,
can we create a user setting for that?
And now we have done. So, in the you
can now override and decide the default
folder that you would like to have for,
for your projects, or the default root
location.
Similarly, for projects, when you are
building apps, then we put those
typically, or normally today, in the
project folder.
But uh maybe you want to reuse those and
support uh having an output folder,
right? And now we we support that. So,
in the AL.
uh compilation options, you can now
specify an out folder for uh your app.
And that, as I said, is usual usual, for
instance, for sharing apps across
projects or even workspaces.
Now, the uh project will still contain a
node for the output file, but it could
physically then be located outside of
the project itself.
So, let's uh have a quick demo uh on uh
GitHub Copilot Chat. I mean, in our last
uh launch event session back in April,
Stefan showcased some examples of using
the GitHub Copilot while authoring AL
code. And let's have a look at the more
recent GitHub Copilot Chat, which is an
interactive chat experience inside of uh
Visual Studio Code. It's basically an
extension uh that uh you install, and it
will give you a chat uh window where you
can interact um ask questions also about
your code, and you will also have some
inline functionality uh in your editor
for interacting.
So, before we go there, you know, what
is it? As I said, it's a chat interface.
Uh it can answer a wide range of
coding-related questions.
Um
Typical use cases could be, you know,
explaining code, proposing code fixes,
answering code questions. In general,
also, you could use it to generate uh
unit test cases.
In In general, again, this is an
assistant tool, right? It's not a
replacement uh for human programming.
And so, you remember to uh review the
generated content, especially for AL,
because the training material is based
on open-source uh code, and for AL,
that's fairly limited. What is there,
you know, the the the results there uh
really vary, but it's just super
interesting to try out. You know, give
us a feedback on it. I put in a link
here about how to start and pricing,
etc. But, let's just switch to the
Visual Studio Code and show a quick uh
demo of this.
I am in Visual Studio uh Code. I have a
project open. This is one of our
AppSource apps, the convert temperature
sample app.
Uh and I've installed GitHub Copilot,
and you see it starts up asking me uh
what you uh you know, what it can help
with me. And it also suggests down here
that I can use a forward slash to see
the commands, right? And it it can offer
me help or to write test or to simplify
code or fix it or explain, etc. It can
also help me create a a workspace.
And so, you know, you can you can ask it
questions about uh you know, what is a
code unit
in AL,
and it will try to answer that. So,
that's sort of the chat experience of
this.
Now, another uh option that you can use
is that you can uh for example, mark uh
some text in source, and you can
right-click, and you can select Copilot,
and you can have it try to explain that.
And that's kind of interesting if you do
not know the source code.
Uh you know, in this case, it's it's
fairly simple, but it will actually it
it's pretty good at explaining uh source
code.
Um so,
I think I think that's probably the the
nicest uh capability right now. You
could do the same here and have it
generate uh for example, uh doc comments
here that you can have then uh be part
of the AL doc updates that you saw Esben
uh show. Okay. So, that was
what I wanted to show. Try it out. Now,
give us feedback.
Uh again, it might not give correct
results, but use it where it gives you
some uh some uh some value, and then it
will improve over time.
Yeah, and to get started, as I said, I
added some links here on billing and how
to install and you can go and play with
this yourself.
So, let's end out with just an update on
AppSource and specifically
transactability. You probably heard
about that.
We have the first wave of functionality
with a per user
pricing model
that support direct sales channel in
Microsoft AppSource. So, that's
primarily credit card. That is
as I'm talking now in public preview,
but on October 9th, that will actually
go into GA.
And then we are working on having CSP
support is actually built but we're in
the in the
in the middle of a private preview with
select partners on this, but that is
also going to come out also as we have
talked about earlier.
Um
we don't have a session on transact for
this release wave because Kurt and
myself did one for release wave one and
that's more or less up to date. So, you
can go into aka.ms/bcpartnerportal
and you can find the a recording from
the last launch event under events. So,
that is the transact capabilities for
Business Central apps.
As I said, we also have the sample app
that you can look at that's interesting
for seeing how we created the
entitlements that sort of create the
mapping between the licenses that you
create in Partner Center for your offer
and then the permissions that you then
grant in the app in Business Central.
Um and I also added a link here to an
updated docs page on these entitlements
that you would have to use to map.
Then we have additional developer
resources.
There's been some collaboration with
partners
that has led to updating much more
detail with examples, etc. The HTTP
client, the reporting, the
extensibility,
um
learn topics. We also have a big
investment in the performance tool kit
that you can go and read off. And then
we have the aka.ms/bciicons,
which has an overview of icons that you
can use as part of developing for
for AL or in AL for BC.
So, there's a number that that you know,
most other sessions make sense, but
there's a number of sessions in the
launch event that you know, specifically
for developers. We have the what's new
in AL go for GitHub about the whole CCD
stories. So, Freddy will talk about
that.
As I said, there's one on performance
tool kit that's super important for
making you know, testing and making sure
that your app performs well. Related to
that and related to troubleshooting is
of course what's new in telemetry.
Uh then for some of the language
features, we have the session around
creating customer-centric onboarding
experiences.
And last but not least, what is new in
Power BI and reporting for developers.
And as with any launch session and just
in general, if you have questions, you
can go to Yammer, you know, join the
discussions on our Twitter account, use
the aka.ms/bcall
to get one landing page with a lot of
links to useful resources.
When you have ideas, submit them to us
and join our themed BC office hours.
Thank you.